A Guide to the Civil War Miscellaneous Collection, 1860-2005 (bulk 1862-1928): SC 0134
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Civil War Miscellaneous Collection,
1860-2005 (bulk 1862-1928)
Special Collections, James Madison University
Harrisonburg-Rockingham Historical Society
SC 0134
.2 cubic feet; 1 box
The Civil War Miscellaneous Collection, 1860-2005 (bulk 1862-1928), consists of Civil War records and letters from soldiers from 1860-1926, as well as twentieth-century materials including newspaper clippings, research, and writing about local Civil War battles and events.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
Collection was deposited by the Harrisonburg-Rockingham Historical Society in April 1991. A student paper based on letters from the collection was added in 2005.
Provenance
When the collection was received from the Harrisonburg-Rockingham Historical Society in 1991, the materials consisted of one box of folders, mostly labeled "Civil War," with no apparent arrangement. After review, three collections were established from the materials: Sons of Confederate Veterans Collection, 1896-1964, SC 0132; United Confederate Veterans Collection, 1893-1938, SC 0133; and Civil War Miscellaneous Collection, 1860-2005, SC 0134.
Bio/Historical Note
Civil War records within the collection were issued by government entities, including the Department of the Interior and the Treasury Department, along with various war offices. Notable individuals with papers represented in this collection include local Shenandoah Valley historian John W. Wayland (1872-1962 and Cassie Moncure Lyne (1875-1955) a Civil War writer and poet from Virginia.
Scope and Content
The Civil War Miscellaneous Collection, 1860-2005 (bulk 1862-1928), consists of one box of materials related to the Civil War. This is an assembled collection, and the order of materials has been imposed by the archivist from the original unordered arrangement.
Civil War records included in the collection consist of muster rolls from the years 1862-1865, certificates of discharge and pension, lists of veterans, and lists of applicants and recipients of the Southern Cross of Honor from the years 1860-1926. Most of these records pertain to Confederate companies and individuals from Rockingham and Shenandoah Counties, but there are also a few records related to companies and soldiers within the Union Army. Other materials include personal letters from Civil War soldiers giving views of camp life and activities in and around Rockingham and Shenandoah Counties, writings by local historian John W. Wayland, twentieth century newspaper clippings relating to the Civil War, letters and poetry by Cassie Moncure Lyne, materials relating to Harrisonburg Civil War museums and monuments, and late nineteenth and early twentieth century bulletins and pamphlets about the Civil War. Please note that not all dates are inclusive.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged topically in four series with item level descriptions of folder contents.
Series 1: Primary Source Materials, 1862-1926, 2005
Series 2: Local Civil War History Documents, 1860-1978
Series 3: Museums and Monuments, 1879-1965
Series 4: Pamphlets and Booklets, 1909-1944
Related Material
Sons of Confederate Veterans Collection, 1896-1964, SC 0132, Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University, Harrisonburg, VA.
United Confederate Veterans Collection, 1893-1938, SC 0133, Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University, Harrisonburg, VA.
Location of Originals:
The location of some original letters is unknown.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Foster, George A; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865; McNeill, John Hanson, 1815-1864; Boyd, Belle, 1844-1900; Crook, George, 1828-1890; Kelly, Benjamin Franklin, 1807-1891; Confederate States of America. Army. McNeill Partisan Rangers; Confederate States of America. Army -- Biography; United States. Army. Infantry -- History; Confederate States of America. Army. McNeill Partisan Rangers; Spies -- United States -- Biography; Generals -- United States -- Biography; Presidents -- United States -- Public opinion; Soldiers -- Virginia -- Rockingham County -- Register; Soldiers -- Virginia -- Biography; Soldiers' monuments -- Virginia; Slavery -- United States -- Controversial literature; Southern Cross of Honor; Camp Chase (Ohio) -- History; Confederate States of America -- History, Military -- Sources; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Regimental histories; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- African American troops -- Sources; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Secret service, Confederate; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Poetry; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Prisoners and prisons; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Personal narratives, Confederate; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Regimental histories; Virginia -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Registers; Virginia -- History, Local -- 19th century; Rockingham County (Va.) -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865
- Series 1: Primary Source Materials, 1862-1926, 2005
  - Primary Source Materials, 1862-1865, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Content
    Four Muster Rolls: Two from Union regiments in Illinois and New Hampshire; one from a Union convalescent regiment in Virginia; and one from Captain George A. Foster's company E, 20th regiment of U.S. Colored Infantry. Notes by Shenandoah Valley historian John Wayland on the muster roll of a company of Confederate infantry in the Virginia Militia.
  - Primary Source Materials, 1862-1865, 2005, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Four letters from Civil War soldiers and one letter from a veteran relating details of his service and life after the Civil War. Project report titled "Civil War Letters Collection."
  - Primary Source Materials, 1863-1914, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Civil War records including an honorable discharge from the Union Army, a pay voucher for a black aide-de-camp in the Union Army, a special orders letter granting a leave of absence, a copy of a receipt from Adams Express Company, a letter from the Treasury Department denying a veteran's claim for pay, and a pension certificate from the Bureau of Pensions.
- Series 2: Local Civil War History Documents, 1860-1978
  - Local Civil War History Documents, 1865-1928, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Records pertaining to Confederate Soldiers, including lists of Confederate companies organized in Rockingham County, rosters of ex-Confederate soldiers in Rockingham County, lists of applicants for the Southern Cross of Honor, records of recipients of the Southern Cross of Honor, and a list of veterans from the Linville District.
  - Local Civil War History Documents, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Scope and Contents
    Writings on the Civil War by historian John Wayland, including descriptions of local battles, chronological lists of Civil War events concerning Harrisonburg and Rockingham County, and a drafts of various texts about the Civil War in Rockingham County.
  - Local Civil War History Documents, 1937-1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Copies of twentieth-century newspaper clippings about Civil War events including an article with photos on Colonel John S. Mosby and Mosby's Rangers.
- Series 3: Museums and Monuments, 1879-1965
  - Museums and Monuments, 1922, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Letters to Cassie Moncure Lyne thanking her for sending copies of her poem "The Rockingham Confederate Flag," from various individuals as well as the Library of Virginia, and the Virginia Historical Society. Notes, sketches, and papers relating to Ms. Lyne's desire to have a Confederate Monument erected in Court Square in Harrisonburg, Virginia, along with information about existing Confederate Monuments in Winchester and Richmond, Virginia. Copies of three poems written by Ms. Lyne.
  - Museums and Monuments, 1961-1965, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Letters and documents pertaining to the Civil War Centennial Museum of Harrisonburg, Virginia, documenting the creation of a sign for the museum and relating to the Electric Map of the Stonewall Jackson Valley Campaign housed at the museum.
- Series 4: Pamphlets and Booklets, 1898-1927
  - Pamphlets and Booklets, 1898-1927 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Bulletin of the Virginia State Library, 1927 "Two Confederate Items," includes the "Diary" of Captain H. W. Wingfield of Hanover County, Virginia and the "Reminiscences" of Judge E. C. Moncure of Caroline County, Virginia. An Address by Abraham Lincoln delivered before the R.E. Lee Camp, No. 1, Confederate Veterans, 1909. Miss Rutherford's Scrapbook, "Valuable Information About the South: History of Slavery—The South Did Not Fight to Hold Slaves," 1925. Various informational booklets about Camp Chase, Ohio, and the activities of various Civil War veterans groups.
  - Pamphlets and Booklets, 1900, 1944, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    "Bell Boyd: Southern Spy of the Shenandoah" by Laura Virginia Hale, undated. "Constitution and By Laws of the Stonewall Brigade Band," 1900. "Two Generals Kidnapped," An account of the capture of General George Cook and Benjamin Kelly by McNeill's Rangers, 1944. "McNeill's Last Charge," An account of Captain John H. McNeill and his Rangers, 1944.